Inventory of the Gino Charles Speranza papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Italy subject file, 1904-1926 (Box 11-15:)
  - Wilson, Woodrow. Speeches (Italian), 1919 (Folder 15: 11)
  - Woman's Land Army of America, 1918. (I-21) (Folder 15: 12)
  - Women and women's groups, circa 1916. (II-3.11) (Folder 15: 13)
    Includes leaflets of Esercito Donne Interalleate, Brigata Roma
  - "Yugoslavs and Oppressed Races,", 1918-1919 (II-3.36) (Folder 15: 14-16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1904-1917 (II-3.26) (Folder 15: 17)
- Clippings, 1914-1926 (Box 16-19: 14-16)
  Contains clippings, mostly from Italian newspapers and magazines.
  Arranged in groups by language or form of clipping
  - Newspaper clippings, 1914-1927 (Folder 16-18:)
    - American. (I-13 and I-7-8) (Folder 16:)
      - 1915 (Folder 16: 1)
      - 1922-1927 (Folder 16: 2)
    - French, 1914 (Folder 16: 3)
    - German, 1914-1922 (Folder 16: 4)
    - Italian. (I-13) (Folder 16-18:)
      Includes clippings from Avanti!, Corriere della serra, Giornale d'Italia, Il Marzocco, La Nazione, Il Nuovo giornale, Il Popolo d'Italia, Il Tempo, La Tribuna, L'Unitá
      - Undated (Folder 16: 5-6)
      - Circa 1914-1918 (Folder 16: 7)
      - 1914 (Folder 16: 8)
      - 1915 (Folder 16: 9-11)
      - 1915 (Folder 17: 1-2)
      - 1916 (Folder 17: 3-6)
      - 1917-1926 (Folder 17: 7)
      - Circa 1919-1926 (Folder 17: 8)
      - 1919 (Folder 17: 9)
      - 1920 (Folder 17: 10)
      - 1921 (Folder 18: 1)
      - 1922 (Folder 18: 2)
      - 1923-1926 (Folder 18: 3)
    - Scrapbooks of Italian newspaper clippings, 1915-1916 (Folder 18:)
      - During the war, 1915-1916 (Folder 18: 4-5)
        Includes one scrapbook devoted to clippings about the Austrian offensive of May 1916 (I-15)
      - After the war, 1919-1920. (I-14) (Folder 18: 6)
  - American magazine and journal clippings about Italy, 1909, 1915-1923. (I-12) (Folder 18: 7)
  - Italian magazine and journal clippings, 1914-1926 (Folder 18-19:)
    Most from Le Carnet mondain (French), Il Carroccio, La Lettura, Rassegna Italiana, Touring club Italiano (Rivista mensile), and La Voce
    - 1914-1919 (Folder 18: 8)
    - 1914-1925 (Folder 19: 1)
    - 1915-1916. (I-19) (Folder 19: 2)
    - 1918-1921. (I-27) (Folder 19: 3)
    - Circa 1919-1926. (I-10) (Folder 19: 4)
    - 1919-1922. (I-10) (Folder 19: 5)
    - 1924-1926. (I-10) (Folder 19: 6)
  - Typescript copies of Italian newspaper clippings, manifestoes, and notices, attached to original diaries, 1915-1919 (Folder 19:)
    - Volumes VII-X, 1915-1917. (IV-28) (Folder 19: 7)
    - Volumes XI-XII, 1917-1919. (IV-28) (Folder 19: 8)
- Photographs and postcards, 1918-1934 (Box 20:)
  Contains prints, postcards, and clippings of images.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - American hospital in Florence. (I-14) (Folder 20: 1)
  - Animals at the front. (I-8) (Folder 20: 2)
  - Aviation. (I-27) (Folder 20: 3)
  - Bombarded places. (I-9) (Folder 20: 4)
  - Cemeteries, graves, and monuments. (I-32) (Folder 20: 5)
  - Cities, towns, and buildings at the front. (I-31) (Folder 20: 6)
  - Engineering and supplies. (I-10) (Folder 20: 7)
  - French and Belgian war scenes. (I-33) (Folder 20: 8)
  - Navy. (I-24) (Folder 20: 9)
  - Personages. (I-15) (Folder 20: 10)
  - Poison gases. (I-28) (Folder 20: 11)
  - Prisoners. (I-25) (Folder 20: 12)
  - Protection of art treasures. (I-26) (Folder 20: 13)
  - Scenes at the front I. (I-7) (Folder 20: 14)
  - Scenes at the front II. (I-23) (Folder 20: 15)
  - Soldiers and cavalrymen. (I-19) (Folder 20: 16)
  - Venice. (I-6) (Folder 20: 17)
- Florence Colgate Speranza file, 1916-1918 (Box 21:)
  Contains correspondence, diary, identification documents, and postcards.
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Folder 21: 1)
  - Diary. "Notes in Italy,", 1916 June 11-1917 December 27 (Folder 21: 2)
  - Permission to travel in Italy, 1918 June (Folder 21: 3)
  - Postcards of Italian places, undated (Folder 21: 3)
- Scrapbooks, 1909-1941 (Box 22-38:)
  Contains photographs, postcards, memorabilia, clippings, programs, maps, medals, currency, and dried flowers.
  - Volume I. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 1-52, of published diary (Folder 22:)
  - Volume II. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 53-105, of published diary (Folder 23:)
  - Volume III. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 106-155, of published diary (Folder 24:)
  - Volume IV. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 156-203, of published diary (Folder 25:)
  - Volume V. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 204-241, of published diary (Folder 26:)
  - Volume VI. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 242-282, of published diary (Folder 27:)
  - Volume VII. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 283-310, of published diary (Folder 28:)
  - Volume VIII. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 311-347, of published diary (Folder 29:)
  - Volume IX. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 348-384, of published diary (Folder 30:)
  - Volume X. Corresponds to Volume I, pages 385-406, of published diary (Folder 31:)
  - Volume XI. Corresponds to Volume II, pages 1-43, of published diary (Folder 32:)
  - Volume XII. Corresponds to Volume II, pages 44-71, of published diary (Folder 33:)
  - Volume XIII. Corresponds to Volume II, pages 72-95, of published diary (Folder 34:)
  - Volume XIV. Corresponds to Volume II, pages 96-169, of published diary (Folder 35:)
  - Volume XV. Corresponds to Volume II, pages 170-224, of published diary (Folder 36:)
  - Volume XVI. Corresponds to Volume II, pages 225-268, of published diary (Folder 37:)
  - Volume XVII. Corresponds to Volume II, pages 269-315, of published diary (Folder 38:)
- Oversize materials, 1911-1925 (Box 39, Map case:)
  Contains newspapers, broadsides, lithographs, balance sheet, report, poster, and map.
  - Balance sheet of the American War Relief in Florence, 1915 October (Folder 39: 1)
  - Broadsides (Folder 39: 1)
    - Announcement by General Cardona, circa 1915 (Folder 39: 1)
    - "Commissione Comunale Pro Disoccupati,", 1915 March 23 (Folder 39: 1)
    - "Perché siamo in guerra?", undated (Folder 39: 1)
    - Societá Umbra per la Protezione degli Animali (PERUGIA), undated (Folder 39: 1)
  - Lithographs of advertisements for war loans, 1917 (Folder 39: 1)
    See also Subject file: War loans
  - Newspapers (Folder 39:)
    - American and British (Folder 39: 2)
      - The Evening Mail (incomplete), 1918 November 23 (Folder 39: 2)
      - The New York Evening Post (incomplete), 1915 November 19; 1918 February 18 (Folder 39: 2)
      - The New York Herald Tribune (incomplete), 1925 June 9 (Folder 39: 2)
      - The New York Times(incomplete), 1915 December 8 (Folder 39: 2)
      - The Stars and Stripes, 1918 March 22 (Folder 39: 2)
    - Italian (Folder 39: 3-4)
      - I Campi (Settimanale agricolo), 1919 March 9 (Folder 39: 3)
      - Corriere della serra, 1916 March 20 (incomplete); 1916 June 11; 1916 August 30; 1919 April 25 (Folder 39: 3)
      - Corriere di Romagna, 1916 June 20-21 (Folder 39: 3)
      - La Difesa, 1915 October 27-28 (Folder 39: 3)
      - Gazzetta ferrarese, 1916 June 24 (Folder 39: 3)
      - L'Idea nazionale, 1916 March 20 (Folder 39: 3)
      - L'Italia all'estero, 1911 July 15-31 (Folder 39: 3)
      - Il Marzocco, 1912 September 29; 1912 October 20; 1913 September 21; 1914 March 8; 1915 May 15 (Folder 39: 4)
      - Il Mattino, 1918 November 11-12 (incomplete); 1919 April 30-May 1 (Folder 39: 4)
      - Sior tonin bonagrazia, 1915 October 16 (Folder 39: 4)
      - Unititled, undated (Folder 39: 4)
  - Printed lyrics to popular songs and war songs, undated (Folder 39: 5)
    See also Subject file: Popular songs and war songs
  - Report of statistical figures of the city of Fiume, 1919 February (Folder 39: 5)
  - Map of Red Cross centers in Italy, 1918 March-September (I-30) (Folder Map case:)
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1917-1930
  - 2015 May release of records, 1917-1930 (Box-folder 40:1-41:3)